A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Human Rights and International Cooperation (HRIC), Office Files of Mahnaz lspahani FA597
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Human Rights and International Cooperation (HRIC), Office Files of Mahnaz lspahani
1969-2002, bulk 1990-2002
Rockefeller Archive Center
lspahani, Mahnaz
Ford Foundation
FA597
16.8 Cubic Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Records are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement
Arranged in 9 series by file type.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Chronological Correspondence, 1991-2002
Series II. Consultants, 1993-2001
Series III. Board of Trustees, 1995-2001
Series IV. Liason Grants, 1990-1998
Series V. ICT Scholar in Residence, 1998-2001
Series VI. Meetings, 1992-2001
Series VII. Organization Files, 1993-1999
Series VIII. Regional Files, 1993-1999
Series IX. Subject Files, 1969-2000
Scope and Contents
Contains correspondence, liason grants, board of trustees materials, consultants files, ICT Scholar-In-Residence materials, meeting records, organization files, regional files and subject files.
Biographical / Historical
Mahnaz Ispahani Bartos is a foreign policy expert, jewelry dealer, former foundation executive, and author who worked for ten years at the Ford Foundation. She joined the Foundation as a Program Officer in the International Affairs Program in 1992 and later became Deputy Director of the Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ) Human Rights and International Cooperation unit (HRIC).
In addition to her work at the Ford Foundation, Ispahani worked as a senior fellow for South Asia at the Council on Foreign Relations where she directed the Roundtable on South Asia and U.S. Policy. She had other fellowships at the Harvard University Belfer Center and the Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars at the Smithsonian Institution. She has also been an advisor to the Carnegie Corporation and the Open Society Institute. In 2013, she started her business, the Mahnaz Collection which is a jewelry gallery in New York City.
Ispahani was born in East Pakistan (present day Bangladesh). Her family owns and manages the Ispahani Group, a Bangladeshi conglomerate. Her grandfather Mirza Abul Hassan Isaphani served as Pakistan's first ambassador to the United States. Mahnaz Ispahani is married to photographer Adam Bartos.
Ispahani earned a B.A. in English literature and political science from Wellesley College and a Ph.D. and Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy from the Tufts University Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy.
- Chronological Correspondence, 1991-2002; I
  - Shepard Forman Chrons, 1991-1996 (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons, 1992 September-1993 July (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Memoranda, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons, Jul 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons (A-M), 1995 (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons (Mc-Z), 1995 (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) E-mail, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Memoranda, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons (A-K), 1997 (Box 2)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons (L-Z), 1997 (Box 2)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons, 2001-January 2002 (Box 2)
- Consultants, 1993-2001; II
  - Anderlini, Sanam and Two Twelve, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Ashton, Sarah, 1994-1999 (Box 3)
  - Atwood, Brian, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Bukovansky, Mlada, 1993-2000 (Box 3)
  - Butegwa, Florence, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Castaneda, Jorge, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Findlay, Matthew, 1994-1997 (Box 3)
  - Forman, Shep, circa 1996 (Box 3)
  - Friedman, Thomas L., 1999 (Box 3)
  - Gopinath, Meenakshi, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Higashi, Taryn, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
  - Hessini, Leila, 1995-1997 (Box 3)
  - Keary, Lisa, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Lindblom, Lance, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Luck, Ed -- UN Review, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Montes, Manuel F. (Butch), 1999-2000 (Box 3)
  - Peniston, Mary, 1997-1999 (Box 3)
  - Sen, Amartya, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Shaheed, Fareeda, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Sick, Gary, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Stern, Jessica, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Tendler, Judith, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Whitfield, Teresa, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Wiseman, Geoffrey, 1993 (Box 3)
- Board of Trustees, 1995-2001; III
  - Board of Trustees Meeting, 1995 March (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 1995 December (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 1996 March (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 1996 June (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees Meeting, 1996 June 26 (Box 4)
  - Transition -- Portfolio Reviews, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Transition -- PEG Transition, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Transition -- Miscellaneous Memoranda, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 1996 December (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 1997 June (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 1997 September (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees Presentation, 1998 January (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 1998 January (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 1998 May (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 1998 September (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 1999 January (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 1999 May (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 1999 September (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 2000 January (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 2000 May 23-24 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 2000 September (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 2001 January (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 2001 May (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 2001 September (Box 4)
- Liason Grants, 1990-1998; IV
  - Liason Grants A-C, 1990-1998 (Box 5)
  - Liason Grants D-N, 1990-1998 (Box 5)
  - Liason Grants O-Z, 1990-1998 (Box 5)
- ICT Scholar in Residence, 1998-2001; V
  - Background Papers, 1998-2000 (Box 6)
  - CCMC, 1999 (Box 6)
  - CCMC, 2000 (Box 6)
  - Columbia (Box 6)
  - ICT Finalists -- Deibert, Ronald, 2001 (Box 6)
  - ICT Scholar Background Memoranda, 2000 (Box 6)
  - ICT Scholar -- Miscellaneous Memoranda and Background, 2000 (Box 6)
  - ICT Scholar -- Miscellaneous Memoranda, 200-2001 (Box 6)
  - Information Technology and International Cooperation, 1999-2000 (Box 6)
  - IT Background -- S. Neill, 2000 (Box 6)
  - Kumdr Paper and Contacts in India, 2000 August 28 (Box 6)
  - New Technologies and International Cooperation Meeting, 2001 July 11 (Box 6)
  - Technology, 1999 (Box 6)
- Meetings, 1992-2001; VI
  - IAP Retreat -- Swift River Inn, 1992 October 7-10 (Box 7)
  - IAP Worldwide Meeting -- Lisbon, Portugal, 1992 November 9-13 (Box 7)
  - Work File -- Lisbon Conference, 1992 November 9-13 (Box 7)
  - Lisbon Samples -- Correspondence, Agenda, 1992-1994 (Box 7)
  - Moscow Briefing Book, 1993 September 26-30 (Box 7)
  - Board of Trustees Overseas Program Review, 1993 September 26-October 2 (Box 7)
  - Board of Trustees Program Review -- Prague, 1993 September 26-October 2 (Box 7)
  - Budapest/Prague, 1993 September 26-October 2 (Box 7)
  - Varieties of Muslim Experience Conference -- Istanbul, Turkey, 1994 June 11-16 (Box 7)
  - Muslim Societies Meeting Briefing Book, 1994 June 11-16 (Box 7)
  - Varities of Muslim Experience -- Istanbul, 1994 June 11-16 (Box 7)
  - Muslim Societies Meeting -- Background and Final Report, 1994 June (Box 7)
  - Beijing Plus 5, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Beijing Conference -- Grant-related, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Beijing Conference -- Memoranda/Email, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Beijing Conference -- Platforms for Action, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Beijing Conference -- Traveling Material, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Bertelsmann Foundation Symposium -- Gutersloh, Germany, 1996 April 15-17 (Box 8)
  - Program Officer Orientation Meeting, 1996 October 25 (Box 8)
  - Peace Process, Strengthening the, 1996 December 12 (Box 8)
  - Peace Process Meetings, 1997 (Box 8)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Staff Retreat, 1997 January (Box 8)
  - PSJ Meeting, 1997 February 24 (Box 8)
  - New Voices Meeting, 1997 March 10-11 (Box 8)
  - The US Role in the World: New Priorities Abroad and New Voices at Home -- New Voices Meeting Binder, 1997 March 10-11 (Box 8)
  - The US Role in the World: New Priorities Abroad and New Voices at Home -- New Voices Meeting, 1997 March 10-11 (Box 8)
  - The US Role in the World: New Priorities Abroad and New Voices at Home -- New Voices Judith Tendler Report, 1997 August 8 (Box 8)
  - The US Role in the World: New Priorities Abroad and New Voices at Home -- New Voices Correspondence, 1997 (Box 8)
  - The US Role in the World: New Priorities Abroad and New Voices at Home -- New Voices Meeting and Report -- Background, 1997 March 10-11 (Box 8)
  - Human Rights and International Cooperation (HRIC) Retreat, 1997 September (Box 8)
  - PSJ Retreat, 1997 November 12-13 (Box 8)
  - Istanbul Meeting -- Notes and Religion and Gender RGAs, 1998 January (Box 8)
  - Ford Foundation -- Program Division Leadership Group, 1998 February 16-20 (Box 9)
  - Defining International Cooperation, 1998 April 6 (Box 9)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Worldwide Meeting, 1998 May (Box 9)
  - Human Rights and International Cooperation (HRIC) Retreat, 1998 October 1-2 (Box 9)
  - PSJ Program Manager Workshop, 1999 January 4 (Box 9)
  - International Cooperation Brainstorming Meetings, 1999 March-April (Box 9)
  - Ford Foundation Human Rights Meeting, 1999 October 25-27 (Box 9)
  - International Cooperation Meeting, 2000 March 27-29 (Box 9)
  - International Cooperation Meeting Briefing Book and Report, 2000 March 27-29 (Box 9)
  - Ford Foundation -- Transitional Justice Meeting, 2000 April 6 (Box 9)
  - Gender in International Cooperation Meeting, 2000 May 8-9 (Box 9)
  - Women's Leadership and Gender in International Relationships Meeting (1/4), 2000 May 8-9 (Box 10)
  - Women's Leadership and Gender in International Relationships Meeting (2/4), 2000 May 8-9 (Box 10)
  - Women and Gender Meeting (3/4), 2000 May 8-9 (Box 10)
  - Gender Meeting -- Miscellaneous (4/4), 2000 May 8-9 (Box 10)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Worldwide Meeting -- Krakow, Poland, 2000 June 3-9 (Box 10)
  - Program Division Leadership, 2000 March 5-9 (Box 10)
  - International Cooperation (IC) Meeting -- Shanghai, China, 2001 December 13-15 (Box 10)
- Organization Files, 1993-1999; VII
  - Academy for Educational Development, 1998 (Box 10)
  - Carnegie Endowment -- J. Matlock Review of Moscow Center, 1998 (Box 10)
  - Council on Foreign Relations (CFR) Study Group on US Economic Relations in Africa, 1997 (Box 10)
  - Council on Foreign Relations (CFR) -- US Foreign Policy and the Muslim World Study Group (Box 10)
  - Fulbright/Institute of International Education (IIE) (1/2), 1997-1999 (Box 10)
  - Fulbright/Institute of International Education (IIE) (2/2), 1999 (Box 10)
  - Inter-American Dialogue, 1993-1999 (Box 10)
  - Macarthur Foundation, 1993 (Box 10)
  - National Humanities Center -- Fulbright Study, 1997 June 26 (Box 10)
  - New York University -- Center on International Cooperation, 1998-1999 (Box 10)
  - Pacific Council on International Policy (retreat materials, etc), 1998 (Box 10)
  - Stimson Center, 1993-1998 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Development Program, 1996 (Box 10)
  - Women's Foreign Policy Group, 1993-1998 (Box 10)
- Regional Files, 1993-1999; VIII
  - Africa -- Grantmaking in, 1994-1999 (Box 11)
  - Africa -- Human Rights (regional), 1998 (Box 11)
  - African American Institutes, 1994 (Box 11)
  - Africa/Strategy -- the Salih Booker Report, 1993-1996 (Box 11)
  - Africa -- South Africa, 1993 (Box 11)
  - Africa -- Strategy Papers, 1993-1996 (Box 11)
  - Bosnia, 1993 (Box 11)
  - Central America -- General, 1993 (Box 11)
  - Central America -- Initiative Meeting, 1995 September 20 (Box 11)
  - Central America -- Initiative, 1993-1996 (Box 11)
  - Cuba Trip, 1993 March 25-26 (Box 11)
  - Haiti Meeting, 1993 August 5 (Box 11)
- Subject Files, 1969-2000; IX
  - Affirmative Action Working Group, 1999 (Box 12)
  - Dash, Michelle, 1997 (Box 12)
  - Democratization, 1994 (Box 12)
  - Ford Foundation and the Media (news clippings), 1995-1996 (Box 12)
  - Ford Foundation Meetings/Memoranda -- Gener and Religion in International Affairs Meeting Notes, 1996 July (Box 12)
  - Ford Foundation Meetings/Memoranda -- Memoranda prepared by Elizabeth/Mayada/Mlada, 1992-1994 (Box 12)
  - Ford Foundation Meetings/Memoranda -- November 22 Follow-up Meeting, 1994 November 22 (Box 12)
  - Ford Foundation Meetings/Memoranda -- Religion and Gender -- Muslim Societies Meeting Follow-up, 1995 December 18 (Box 12)
  - Ford Foundation -- Old Programs -- "South Asia", 1969-1993 (Box 12)
  - Individuals and Institutions with Special Interest in Religion and Gender -- Catholics for a Free Choice, 1996 June 13 (Box 12)
  - Individuals and Institutions with Special Interest in Religion and Gender -- Sisterhood is Global Institute, 1994-1995 (Box 12)
  - Individuals and Institutions with Special Interest in Religion and Gender -- Religion and Gender -- Muslim Women's League, 1995 (Box 12)
  - Individuals and Institutions with Special Interest in Religion and Gender -- DePaul University/Beverly McCloud -- Islam in America, 1994 (Box 12)
  - International Law Program Officer or Assistant Program Officer, 1992 (Box 12)
  - Israel -- West Bank Gaza Strip, 1999 (Box 12)
  - Kosovo File, 1999 June (Box 12)
  - Middle East Proposals -- Middle East Meetings, 1990 June 26 (Box 12)
  - Middle East Proposals -- Conference to Examine the 1967 Arab-Israeli War, 1990-1991 (Box 12)
  - Middle East Proposals -- Brookings -- Middle East Studies Program, 1991 (Box 12)
  - Migration and Security -- Energy and Security, 1997 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Council on Foreign Relations (CFR) Meeting, 1995 April 25 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Notes of the CFR Meeting, 1995 April 25 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Chronology of Work, 1995 June 30 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Distribution of Notes/Excerpts of CFR Meeting to Foundation Staff, 1996 February 21 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Drafts of Cover Letters and Memoranda re: Distribution of meeting notes, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Excerpts from the CFR Meeting -- Final Version, 1995 April 25 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Meeting Agenda/Invitation Letter, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Memorandum to Charlayne Hunter-Gault, 1995 April 22 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Letters to Participants Transmitting Notes, 1995 December 4 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Memorandum to Mahmaz Ispahani -- List of Issues, 1995 May 11 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Lunch Meeting with S. Bell-Rose, 1995 August 24 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Related Correspondence, 1992-1996 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Thank You Letter to Participants (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- CFR Meeting Recording [CASSETTE TAPES], 1995 April 25 (Box 13)
  - Overseas Development Council, 1993-1995 (Box 13)
  - Peace and Security, 1991 (Box 13)
  - Program Assistant Workshop (J. Jaffre), 1997-1999 (Box 13)
  - Program Assistantship, 1998-2000 (Box 13)
  - Program -- Program Assistants, 1996 (Box 13)
  - Program -- Joint Program Review, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Program -- Program Paper -- International Affairs, 1994-1995 (Box 13)
  - Program -- Program Review -- International Affairs, 1993 (Box 13)
  - Program -- Program Review -- International Affairs, 1994 (Box 13)
  - Public Policy and International Affairs (PPIA) -- Washington, 1996 November 15 (Box 14)
  - Public Policy and International Affairs (PPIA) -- Meetings, 1995-1996 (Box 14)
  - Public Policy and International Affairs (PPIA), 1996 (Box 14)
  - Public Policy and International Affairs (PPIA) -- Academy for Educational Development, 1999 (Box 14)
  - Religion and Gender -- Muslim Voices -- Responses from Regional Offices, 1994-1995 (Box 14)
  - Religion and Gender -- Muslim Voices -- Previous Ford Foundation Grants related to Muslim Societies, 1979-1994 (Box 14)
  - Religion and Gender -- Muslim Voices -- Biennial Program Review -- Muslim Societies Initiative, 1995 March 21 (Box 14)
  - Religion and Gender -- Muslim Voices -- Strengthening Muslim Women's Voices, 1995 April 18 (Box 14)
  - Religion and Gender -- Film and Media -- Proposals Received, 1995 (Box 14)
  - Religion and Gender -- Film and Media -- Women and Media, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Religion and Gender -- Ongoing Activities, 1993-1995 (Box 14)
  - Religion Meetings with Education, Arts and Culture (EAC) -- Correspondence, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Religion Meetings with Education, Arts and Culture (EAC) -- Culture and Education, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Religion Meetings with Education, Arts and Culture (EAC) -- Culture and Education Reports, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Religion Meetings with Education, Arts and Culture (EAC) -- Culture and Religion Subgroups, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Religion Meetings with Education, Arts and Culture (EAC) -- EAC Transition, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Religion Meetings with Education, Arts and Culture (EAC) -- Muslim Experience Meeting, 1994 June 11-16 (Box 14)
  - Religion Meetings with Education, Arts and Culture (EAC) -- Tarrytown Meeting, 1996 March 4-5 (Box 14)
  - United Nations (UN) Related Material, 1991-1994 (Box 14)
  - Vietnam, 1993-1995 (Box 14)
  - Vietnam -- International Relations Program, 1994 (Box 14)
  - Vietnam -- Meeting with Vice-Minister, 1997 April 25 (Box 14)
  - Women -- Women's Program Forum -- Memoranda, 1992-1997 (Box 14)
  - Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, 1991-1995 (Box 14)
  - Woodrow Wilson -- Minority Fellowships (Nancy Feller), 1995 (Box 14)
  - Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars -- Review of Organization and Management and Conference on Water and Conflict, 1997 (Box 14)